[Music]
hello and welcome to episode 16 of our
inventory tutorial series as well as
episode 5 of the shop system series so
by the end of this video we're going to
be able to pick up all of our items off
the ground we're going to be able to
come over to this shop which doesn't
currently have any poison potions so we
can sell them a poison potion so we sell
items and you can see that as we click
these items it updates the um item
preview panel that we've got here i'm
going to click sell items and sell the
poison potion to the shop the shop now
has a poison potion in stock
i'm going to come over here to the
poison to the potion shop and let's sell
them one of my swords
and they've got a sword in their
inventory i can come over here and we'll
put some items in that chest
put some cogs in this chest and maybe
let's store our sword as well let's save
our game come out let's go back in we
can now load the game all of those items
will disappear because we've already
picked them up we've got our cogs and
our sword in this chest got our potions
in this chest let's make a new stack
because we can why not
you can see that you can see that the
sword item has been stored in the shop
we can check over here and this has got
the poison potion in stock that we sold
them so we've got the shops saving and
loading as well as remembering their
gold and the player gold all of that is
saving quite nicely
that's where we're going to be by the
end of this video so let's just jump
straight into it okay so let's crack on
with uh getting the item preview working
and being able to sell items from the
players inventory to the shop
so let's go over to our inventory system
script here and we're going to start by
displaying the player inventory based on
the tabs at the top so in our refresh um
item display in our shopkeeper display
class we've got this thing here and
currently we're just saying display
player inventory actually what we want
to do is we want to say if
is selling then we want to display the
player imagery
else we want to display the shop
inventory uh display layer inventory
let's cut this
put that there let's go to them okay so
let's check let's start to build this
display player inventory inventory
method
so what we need to do here is we need to
loop through all of the items in the
player's inventory and then display them
in the list on the left hand side of the
shop
so for that we're just going to do a for
each loop
and we're going to go through every item
in the player inventory holder primary
inventory system and then we're going to
make a method called get all items held
which is going to return a dictionary of
items that the player holds so let's
create this method so this is over on
the inventory system.cs script
and
it's currently public i enumerable
i'm going to make it a dictionary of
inventory item data as well as uh an
amount of that so this is going to be
just
a dictionary made up of distinct items
that the player has because currently
the player's inventory is organized into
slots
and those slots can have
the same item in them and multiple
amounts because of the stack splitting
and stack assigning and stuff
so what we need is we need an organized
list of um how many cogs does the player
have we don't care about what stacks
they're in just how many cogs are in the
player's inventory so that's what this
is gonna do here so we're gonna make a
new dictionary called distinct items and
this is going to be a dictionary of uh
inventory item data and an int and this
is what we're going to return
at the end of this method
and here we're going to loop through all
of the items in the players inventory so
we'll do for each
um
item in our
inventory slots if the inventory slots
um if the item.data is equal to null and
we don't have an item in that slot it's
empty so we can just continue which will
skip to the next item in the loop but if
it's not null then we can check this
dictionary to see whether
we've already put the item in it
and so we want to say if
distinct items doesn't contain
e our item.data
which you know the first time this goes
around it won't
and so if distinct item dot contains key
item data and let's add it let's add the
data to the dictionary so item dot data
and the int is going to be how many of
the item we have so stack size and we
can say else so here we're checking if
it doesn't contain the key
then let's add it to the dictionary and
if it does contain the key let's just
increase the amount of the item that
we've got so we can say else
distinct items using the data as the key
and then we can plus equal
item dot stack size and then finally we
can just return our distinct items
dictionary here
so now we have a dictionary and it's
organized by inventory item data and the
amount of that that we've got and that's
looped through all of our slots so now
we're going to make a variable called
temp slot and this is going to be equal
to a new shop slot
because obviously the other shop slots
in the display shop inventory are coming
are being driven by the shop's inventory
list the scriptable object here we're
doing it from the player's inventory so
we're going to make a new temporary
slot to that slot we're going to assign
item and it's going to be our item.key
and
item.value from this dictionary that
we're looping through
and then we're going to instantiate a
shop slot so shop slot
equal to instantiate drop slot prefab
and the item
list content panel
at the transform and then we're going to
initialize that slot by passing in our
temp slot
as well as the shop system
and this is going to be the cell markup
so here we can offer the player more or
less for their items based on the shop
cell markup um and that's it for
displaying the player inventory
everything else should work kind of fine
with it but the one thing we do need to
do is we need to set up the tabs that
change
mode that change kind of you know
whether we're buying items or selling
items so to do that we're going to make
two methods here we're going to do a
public
void on by tab pressed and a public void
on
cell tab rest i'm going to say is
spelling is equal to true if we've
clicked the cell tab
and then we can refresh our display and
if the buy tab is pressed and we're just
going to set it selling to false and
again refresh the display and while
we're here we've got this update item
preview method that we made but never
implemented let's just implement that um
just so we can kind of get everything
tied up in this video so we'll do uh
variable data is equal to the shop slot
ui dot
assigned item slot dot item data
and then we're going to set our item
preview sprite to the data
sprite dot sprite equal to the data dot
icon we're going to set the sprite color
equal to color dot white we can update
the item preview name dot text to equal
the data dot display name
and the item preview description dot
text is equal to the data dot
description and i'm just gonna copy
these
and copy i'm going to go to our clear
item preview um function that we made
method and we're going to paste them in
and then here we can set the sprite to
null
we can make it invisible
we can set the text to an empty string
and we can set the data
the description sorry to a empty string
as well
and now we can copy the clear item
preview method and when we display the
shop window and we call refresh display
it was clearing the slots let's clear
the item preview as well so let's just
check that that is all
working see where we're up to with that
let's pick up some items here we've got
um poison potion health potions some
cogs and two swords
so let's go over to this shop here so
we're currently in buy mode if we click
the cell tab
oh sorry nothing will happen because we
need to hook up those buttons the tabs
don't actually do anything so we'll go
to buy button
we'll get this on click event we'll drag
in our shop controller
shopkeeper display on by tab pressed
and then with the sell button again drag
in the shop ui controller shopkeeper
display
on cell tab pressed so again let's make
sure we pick up some items it will come
over here
pull these
look over here
let's press e
to bring up the shop window now let's
click the sell tab and we see here now
this is the player inventory you see
this shop is actually offering us more
for the potions than um they're actually
worth which is quite good but it is
selling them for 150 g
and we can add these to the
basket here
you can see that the shop's got a
thousand gold if we go over um
the thousand gold mark i don't know if
we'll be able to i don't think there's
enough stuff to go over the 1000 mark i
mean there isn't because we've got shop
gold
because we didn't pick up enough stuff
there was a lot of stuff in the world
but
that's now adding it to the players um
to the shopping cart so now when we
click the sell item button we need to be
able to sell the items like we can buy
items from
the shop
so let's go back over to our script and
we've got private void sell items
on our shopkeeper display so here we're
going to do similar to sort of the buy
items we're going to say if the shop
system dot available gold is less than
the
basket total and let's just return
because we don't want to
continue we don't want to sell anything
to the shop but if the shop does have
enough gold to buy all of the players
items we're to loop through
before each loop
i'm going to loop through every
item in the shopping cart and then we're
going to get
our shop system i'm going to make a new
method called sell item
and there we're going to pass in the key
value pair
e
as well as the qvp
dot value and we'll make that method in
just a second
and then i'm going to do a variable
price is equal to get
modified price
kvp dot key kvp dot value shop system
dot
cell markup and the reason we're not
doing this in here is because we need to
use the price to reduce the gold from
the shop and increase the gold on the
player's inventory what we could do is
pass the price through to sell item
actually let's do that that might make a
little bit more sense so
let's do that so we're going to
calculate the price we'll pass in the
price to this sell item method
and then we can
do player
inventory holder primary inventory
system
dot gain
gold
which will take in the price
let's make this method
in a second over under player inventory
and then we'll do player
inventory holder dot primary inventory
system
and then we'll remove items from
inventory
we're going to remove the key value pair
dot key that's the the item that we're
going to remove and how many of the item
we are going to remove
so let's make this cell item method
first so
this is over on our shop system.cs
script and all this is going to do is
it's going to add to shop
and it's going to add
a
the qpp key and the kvp value
to the shop then we can just call gain
gold and we can pass through the price
so now let's make these two methods on
our inventory system so
i'm gonna implement gain gold
and implement remove items from
inventory so gengold is just going to do
available
nice and simple now for the remove items
from inventory let's get rid of that
i'm gonna rename that to data and
um amount just to keep
that's what i've named kind of all of
the other inventory kind of add in
variables uh makes sense so we're going
to say if
contains item data and we're going to
get back out a list of inventory
slots called in
slot we're going to get out our list of
inventory slots from our contains item
method
and then we're going to see for each
slot in
our inventory slot list we're going to
get the stack size so var stack size and
set that equal to slot dot stack size
and then we can say if
stack size is greater than the amount
that we're trying to remove
from our inventory then we can call slot
dot remove from stack and we can just
remove the amount from that one slot if
however we have but for example if
amount was greater than stack size then
we need to go to the next slot in our
list and remove it from that so we can
say
else slot dot remove from stack stack
size and then from amount that we've
passed in we can minus equal
the stack size then it'll go around
again to the next slot
that has the item in it and it will
remove the next from that stack size
until it's been through them all and we
need to also once the slot has been
modified we need to call on imagery slot
changed and invoke that method you know
that action and pass in the slot and we
just need to add to this remove from
stack function so we want to say here
if
stack size
is less than or equal to
zero then let's clear the slot because
at that point you know it's all gone we
don't need to um so obviously at that
point
we don't want to go into minus we just
want to clear the slot out
once we've got to zero we can just make
it an empty slot
let's go back to shopkeeper display so
we've got cell items here and then we
just need to call refresh display
so let's see if that is working so let's
press play i'm going to come over here
let's pick up these items and we can
come over here we can press e bring up
our shop window over to the sell tab and
let's sell two potions to the shop
so we should see the player gold will
increase by 250 and the shop gold will
reduce by 250. so let's hit sell items
and we've made a little mistake um
instead of gain gold we need to uh
reduce
gold
which isn't a method that we've made so
reduce gold okay so this this is where
this gets a little bit confusing because
we're all um
the way i've named all this is from the
players perspective
so sell item obviously we're a shop so
that can be a bit confusing are we
selling the item to the player or is the
player selling an item to the shop
system i've gone from the point of view
of the player because it's the player
that's doing
kind of the acts in the world
so when we sell an item and call this
we're selling the player is selling an
item to the shop
so it's going to add to the shop and
then we need to reduce the shop's gold
amount so let's hit play and just make
sure that works as planned so let's go
pick up all of this stuff press e sell
two of our other let's buy
let's
go over to our cell tab so
let's sell
two health potions and we can see here
that the description the item preview it
shows the last item that we clicked so
we try and add a cog to the basket
it'll display this is a cog
and we can remove that cog from the
basket and then let's sell our items so
now you can see the player gold
increased by 250 and the shop gold
reduced by 750
and then if we go back over to the buy
tab we can see now that the health
potions have been added to the bottom
of the list and we've got a bit of an
issue here so you can see that it's
added them to the shop but it's also
added them at the bottom of the list
there so let's just figure out what's
going on there
let me just sell those items to the shop
go to the buy tab okay so there's a
little bit of a bug there it is adding
it to the shop but we're getting this um
these additional items as well which we
don't obviously want so let's figure out
what's going on there okay so the
problem was uh we just need to return so
when we on the shop system script we've
got our add to shop function once we've
added it to the stack we needed to call
return so what was happening is we were
adding it to the stack and then we were
also assigning it to a free slot so if
we just put return in our ad to shop
function on the shop system script that
should solve that issue that we were
having let's just confirm that let's
pick up some items go here go to the
sell tab we'll sell the items to the
shop so there's three cogs we can hit
the sell button the store sold the money
go back over to the buy tab
and now we can see that the cogs have
increased the health potions increase
but we've not actually got
in the bottom um that issue that we will
have into and then we can buy items from
the shop so we're going to spend
610 of the player gold
and
increase the shop gold by 610 so let's
buy and then we can go over to the cell
tab and now we can see we've got our
four health potions and five cogs
and we'll sell the cogs back you can see
there's a bit of an issue there the
rounding seems to
be having a bit of a problem let's
figure out why that was okay so that was
a quick change all we needed to do um in
our get modified price it was rounding
up we just needed to round down so
instead of round to win i've put floor
to int
and that's on the shopkeeper display so
that's what that issue was there
and so one of the kind of other things
that we want to do um is be able to save
and load our shop system um to kind of
reflect that we've
you know the shop has gained and lost
stuff and the place that we do that is
over on our shopkeeper.cs
script
so over on our shopkeeper script just
like we've done with our other um
save and load
items what we want to do is in awake
we're going to store a reference to our
id so let's do private string id and
then here we'll say in a way id
equals
get component
unique id
and let's get the id of the npc and then
we're going to make some shop save data
so
outside of our class we'll do
public class shop
save data and we can do system
dot serializable for our shop save data
and this is gonna hold a public shop
system
uh reference in it which i'll call shop
this could take in a position and a
rotation if you wanted so for example if
the shopkeeper kind of wandered around
you could save that data um
i'm just gonna keep it basic though so
we'll do i'm just going to store the
shop system for now but just so you know
you can store other stuff in this like
whatever you care about for your shop
and i'm just going to say public shop
save
data
this is the constructor and it's just
going to take in a
shop system which i'll call
drop system and you guessed it we'll do
shop system equals shop system so back
up to awake we're going to get the id
here
and under that we can say shop
save data which we're going to keep a
reference to so private
shop save data
old
shop save
data let's a shop save
data is equal to new shop save data
passing in our shop system in a start
method so private start we're going to
make a new dictionary on our save game
manager
and just like we did with the chests
they're all stored in a dictionary if
you think about it the npcs are kind of
like chests but slightly different so we
can do if save
game manager dot data we'll do dot um
and i'm gonna do shop keeper
dictionary
and and then we'll check whether the
dictionary contains the key of our id so
let's make this um shopkeeper dictionary
over on our save game manager it's gonna
be save data this class so i'll do this
underneath our chop uh our chest
pictures i'll do public serializable
dictionary taking in a string and um
some shop saved data and we'll call this
the shopkeeper dictionary and then here
we'll do shopkeeper dictionary is equal
to a new serializable dictionary of
string and shop save data so if it
contains the id let's uh so if it
doesn't already contain the id we'll do
savegamemanager.data.shopkeeperdictionary.ad
id
and shop save data and i'm going to
rename this to be consistent to just
have an underscore and then in our on
enable function we can say save load
dot on load game and we'll do load
inventory which will be a new method
that we make as well as on disable copy
this paste in here
and we'll unsubscribe from it
then we're going to make this load
inventory method which takes in some
save data which i'll just call data and
here we'll say if the data dot shop
keeper dictionary and we'll try and get
our id out of the dictionary if it does
exist if the value
is there and we're going to get out the
shop
save data which i'll just call shop save
data and we'll return so
um if the shopkeeper dictionary doesn't
have a reference to the current
shopkeeper then we'll just return but if
it does then we can say our shop save
data is equal to shop save data which is
this here and then we can say our shop
system is equal to the shop save data
dot shop system so again this save and
loading this way of doing save and
loading is what we've done with the
player inventory what we've done with
this the chest inventory what we've done
with the stuff that's on the ground so
that should hopefully all make sense to
you if not maybe go back and watch the
save data video again
um that should work we may have an issue
with the unique ids so if i go over to
our shop and pcs so i just i want to
make sure that these ids stay the same
so 2d
we'll hit play okay so that's staying
the same there's no errors there from
console and i'm going to get rid of this
debug.log though so let's hit play
let's just check that this is working so
i'm going to go over
pick up these items to our shop i'm
going to it's got 99 cogs i'm gonna buy
let's say buy nine cogs we'll buy them
from the shop
we'll sell them a poison potion so sell
items that's now there in the shop if i
close the shop
and walk away go back so
that's all working it's got 90 cogs one
poison potion
let's hit save so we can see saving game
let's exit come back in so it's reset to
default let's load our game we see that
the stuff that we'd already picked up
has gone we've got the cogs that we
bought in our inventory
and the poison potion is there and the
cogs are all gone in the shop
that's the saving the loading of the
shop done um one thing i do really want
to quickly do because it's annoying to
me
is on our ui manager that we made the ui
controller in an update function i'm
just going to say if
keyboard dot current dot get a
scape key that was pressed this frame
then i want to set the shopkeeper
display
to
false just so i can close the shop
without having to keep uh
actually selecting the game object so
that's pretty much it for the shop
system that's all
done i don't think there's anything else
we need to cover
i thought maybe there'd be a couple more
episodes left but there's only i think
that's everything done unless there's
something ridiculously glaring
i may have to pop in from the future
while editing this to
say
that that's the case but
i mean that's all that's all working
that's the shop inventory done we can
close these shop windows now with the
escape key which makes it a lot easier
we've got all of our items on the ground
which we can pick up
we can come over here we can put
poison potion and some cogs in this
chest
in this chest we'll put a sword
to this shop we will sell a sword we'll
save our game
we'll come back in we'll hit play we
will load the game they'll all go got a
sword in that chest poison potion and a
cog in this chest
and they've got one more sword than they
had earlier so yep that's
that's all working i've got the save and
load in um i hope this i hope this
series was enjoyable and you kind of got
it all if there's any big glaring issues
that you need some
like clarity on um
let me know in the comments or join the
discord server where i'll be able to
help you a bit better um if there's like
frequently asked questions then i'll
probably do a follow-up video or maybe
like a code review or something
um but for now thanks for all your
support from this series i'm gonna take
a little break from this inventory
tutorial series while i just think up of
kind of what i want to do next
um i may
do in a couple of weeks a
crafting system so it was quite simple
to set up so if you want to
see how we can use items from our
inventory
to work in a crafting system do let me
know what i may do though is do a bit
more of a general crafting system video
and i'll probably mention in that on how
we could probably hook this into the
system uh just to make it a bit more
generic but for now thanks for watching
and i'll see you in the next one bye
i'd just like to take a minute to thank
all of my patrons on screen now we can
see the 10 000 xp tier which is a sector
sweep and i want to thank all of the 4
000 xb tier members as well
you